Let's take a look at shell script basics:
positional parameters
When writing shell scripts, there is often
a need to accept one or more command line
parameters from the user at the time the script
is executed.
Let's create a very basic shell script. This
script will print a simple message.
In order to run a new script, we have to modify
the permission settings for the script file
to enable the script to be executed.
This command enables execution permission
for the user and group associated with the
file. Next, let's try running the script
The script ran, printing our simple message.
Now let's take a look at our first positional
parameter: $0. Within a shell script, $0 contains
the name of the shell script, as it was called
when the script was executed.
We see that our script successfully obtained
and printed the name of the script.
If we call the script with an absolute path,
$0 will contain the value of that full absolute
path.
Now let's modify the script to accept an additional
command line argument:
After making this modification, our script
will now accept a single command line argument.
Note that bash processed the provided command
line argument and made it available to our
script as a variable. We didn't have to declare
the variable. Bash does that for us. Let's
look at that script again:
The value of the command line argument can
be accessed using the $1 variable.
Shell scripts can accept more than one argument.
Bash supports multiple positional parameters.
Bash actually supports more than 9 positional
parameters. However, to access them you will
need to use the curly brace syntax for accessing
bash variables. Instead of simply typing $ and
then the variable name, the variable name
is surrounded by curly braces.
We can also ask bash how many positional parameters
were supplied by the user. This information
is provided by
the $# variable.