Let's take a look at command line basics:
ls and cd
ls and cd are two of the most commonly used
commands.
Let's take a look.
If I run ls with no arguments, it's going
to display the contents of the current working
directory.
So, we have just seen that in this directory,
there is a single subdirectory called Homeworks.
ls also accepts an argument.
When I provide an argument to ls, it will
list the contents of that directory rather
than the current directory.
So here we see there are several subdirectories
within the /usr directory.
Let's take a look at the root.
So this is the root of the file system.
Now let's take a look at cd.
cd is used to change directories.
So currently I am in my home directory.
We can verify this by running pwd to print
the current working directory.
We see that this is my home directory.
Now let's use cd to change to a different
directory.
So let's go to /usr
Now, if I run ls with no commands, with no
parameters, it's going to print the contents
of the current working directory, which is
/usr.
If I run cd with no arguments, it will take
me back to my home directory.
So keep in mind that both cd and ls can be
run with no parameters.
If ls is run with no parameters, it will print
the contents of the current working directory.
If cd is run with no parameters, it will take
you to your home directory.
If ls is run with a parameter, it will display
the contents of that directory.
If cd is run with a parameter, you will change
to that directory, and the directory that
you provided as the argument will become your
new current working directory.
So just now, I used cd to change to a directory
called /bin, and once inside that directory,
I ran ls to list the contents.
This directory contains a lot of executable
files.
Now let's go back to our home directory, and
look at the manual page for ls.
ls has quite a few options.
Many of them, you'll never use but there are
a few that are definitely very useful.
To begin with let's take a look at the -a
command.
Looking at the manual, you can see that by
default ls will ignore entries whose names
begin with a period.
In the home directory, we run ls and it appears
that there is only one item.
We run ls -a, we see that there are in fact
a number of additional files that begin with
the period.
These files are all ignored unless the -a
flag is provided to ls.
-a and --all are two ways of typing the same
thing.
You can see this in the manual page; that
they are provided on the same line.
And that's the way, that's the correct way
to interpret items like this in a manual page.
That when the flags are on the same line,
that means that's two ways of specifying the
same thing.
So let's take a look at some other options
of ls.
One very commonly used flag is the -l flag,
for long listing format.
ls -l is going to provide us with additional
pieces of information, including the permissions
of the file, the owner of the file, the group
of the file, the size of the file, and the
date and time that the file was accessed or
created.
Another flag commonly used in conjunction
with the -l flag is -h.
-h prints the file sizes in human readable
format
Note that when I'm providing I can bunch them
together, or separate them out, and note that
we have a difference here.
We've gone from 4096 to 4.0 kilobytes.
There is a large number of options for ls,
and sometimes it's useful to ask ls to sort
by file size, and other options.
That's all for now.