Let's take a look at command line basics:
pwd
pwd is one of the simple commands that you
need to learn
pwd stands for print working directory
This command gives us the location where we're
currently located in the directory structure
Let's take a look at the manual page
pwd prints the name of the current working
directory
There are a couple of options, which you usually
won't need to use.
When we run pwd, currently, we see that I
am in my home directory
We can explore other places in the file system
and use pwd to identify where we are.
Let's use the cd command to go somewhere else.
Let's try a few more.
You'll see that wherever I go, I can use pwd
to find out the location where I am.